Finding Aid for Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action (University of Michigan) Records, 1964-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action (University of Michigan) records
1964-2004
1974-1988
University of Michigan. Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action.
0550 Bimu, 2
The Personnel Office of the University of Michigan was founded in 1945. This office dealt with the development and implementation of personnel policies and issues of hiring, firing, promotion, tenure, sabbatical leaves, remuneration, and contract negotiations. The records of this office are generally closed for thirty years after their creation. The Affirmative Action Office was created in 1972 to monitor the university's enforcement of federal and state affirmative action legislation such as equal employment opportunity, Title IX, age discrimination in employment act, etc and reporting the university's compliance to the federal and state governments. This office was also responsible for ensuring fair and equitable hiring practices within the university. In February 1994, the two offices were united and reorganized to form the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
21.4 linear feet
Records were transferred from the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action (Donor No. 7384 ) and its predecessors, Personnel Office and Affirmative Action Office in various accessions. Additions are received at regular intervals.
The Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 12-17
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 22
The University of Michigan Personnel Office was established in 1945 to develop and implement personnel policies, administer faculty promotion and tenure-granting policies, and negotiate and monitor contracts with unionized university employees. While recommendations for faculty promotions and tenure began in the department, school, or college, the Personnel Office was responsible for conducting them to the president, the provost, and to the Board of Regents for final action. This office also maintained the official employment record for all university faculty and staff. The Personnel Office annually published salary information of all university employees. Researchers will find these listings in the University of Michigan Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action publications group.
In 1972 the University of Michigan created the Affirmative Action Program to develop recruiting practices and set goals and timetables to respond to federal laws passed in the 1960s guaranteeing equal opportunity in employment to women and minorities. The first director of the Affirmative Action Program was Nellie M. Varner. Her chief responsibility was to interpret the specific guidelines of the Department of Education (Title VI, Title IX), the Department of Labor (Title IV and Title VII) and to build a structure within the university to meet these guidelines. In addition she served as a liaison between the university, federal government officials, and the university's Commissions for Minority Affairs and Women, established by President Robben Fleming in 1971. His charge to the commissions was to examine university policies, procedures, and practices which might contribute to discrimination against minority groups and women, and make recommendations. The commissions and the Affirmative Action Program worked together to develop procedures and submitted recommendations to the president to improve various programs within the university.
Reorganized in 1976 the Affirmative Action Program was changed to Affirmative Action Office and the Commissions for Minority Affairs and Women were integrated into the office. The move eliminated duplication of effort and focused activity on the eradication of discriminatory practices. Gwendolyn Baker was appointed the new director of the Affirmative Action Office. In 1978 Charles Allemand replaced her as director of the Affirmative Action Office.
During the 1970s and 1980s, the role of the office grew to include the protection of handicapped individuals, people between the ages of 40 and 70, and veterans of the Vietnam War. In addition, non-discriminatory policies included religion, national origin, height, weight, marital status, and sexual orientation.
In 1980 Virginia Nordby became director of the Affirmative Action Office. The office was divided into compliance and programs teams, reflecting the major functions of the office, to meet federal affirmative action guidelines, and to serve the needs of groups or individuals on campus protected by nondiscrimination laws. Nordby directed both teams.
The compliance team was responsible for the data retrieval, analysis, and writing the reports on minority student recruitment and retention, faculty and staff employment, and affirmative action compliance required by the university and the federal government. In addition, it monitored the race and gender composition of the faculty, staff, and student body; set affirmative action goals and followed their progress, and oversaw faculty and staff recruitment. The program team addressed the needs of members of protected groups through grievance counseling, program development, and policy recommendations. It also provided workshops to the university community.
The Affirmative Action Office also worked with constituency groups, providing direct staff and financial support to such groups as the Academic Women's Caucus, the African-American Organizations Coalition, the Age Concerns Council, the Association of Black Professionals and Administrators, the Commission for Women, the Women of Color Task Force, the Men of Color Task Force, the Task Force on Sexual Orientation, and the Women's Initiative Group.
In 1988 Virginia Nordby left the Affirmative Action Office. Mary Ann Swain became the interim director. In 1989, Zaida I. Giraldo became the director. In 1992, Jimmy A. Myers took over the position as Interim Director.
On February 15, 1994 the Affirmative Action Office combined with the Personnel Office to become the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action. Jackie McClain was appointed as the executive director.
The Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action records (20.4 linear feet) are divided into three subgroups: Affirmative Action, Personnel, and Human Resources and Affirmative Action.
Subjects:
Affirmative action programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Discrimination in employment--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Affirmative Action Office.; University of Michigan. Personnel Office.; University of Michigan. Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action.; University of Michigan. Academic Women's Caucus.; University of Michigan. Center for the Education of Women.; University of Michigan. Center for Continuing Education of Women.; University of Michigan. Commission for Women.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan--Employees.Employees.; University of Michigan. Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; DVDs.
- Affirmative Action
  The Affirmative Action records (11 linear feet) dating from 1964 to 2001, document the university's effort to comply with state and federal laws concerning both racial and sexual harassment, fair and equal employment opportunities, and handicap issues. These records are divided into five series: Topical Files; Federal Agencies and Regulations; Minorities; State of Michigan; and Women.
  - Topical Files
    The Topical Files series (1.2 linear feet) (1972-1996) includes correspondence from the office of Zaida Giraldo dating from 1989 to 1993 as well as an alphabetical administrative topical file. The bulk of this series describes grievance procedures and includes reports on harassment and discrimination, both racial and sexual, within the university from 1985 to 1995. Researchers will also find folders on topics such as family and dependent care, family housing, and the merger of the Affirmative Action Office and the Personnel Office in 1994.
    - Administrative Services Personnel Office, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Committee on Affirmative Action Programs, 1979-1981; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action Office Staff Meeting Agendas, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action Policies regarding Asians, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Conflict Resolution Retreat, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Zaida Giraldo, 1989-1993 (Box 1)
    - Data Policies regarding University of Michigan Policy in Handling Personal Information, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Databases, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Diversity, 1986-1991; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Employment Task Force, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Equal Employment Opportunity Enforcement, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
    - Facilitator Network, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Fair Teaching Group, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Family and Dependent Care, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Family Housing, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Grievance Information System, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Grievance Reports
      - Affirmative Action Grievance Reports, 1991 (Box 1)
      - Comparisons of Equity of Response between Staff and Faculty, undated (Box 1)
      - Grievance Reports, 1985-1987; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Grievance and Harassment Reports, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Racial Discrimination Reports, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
      - Reports of Harassment and Discrimination from Other Units, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Response to SACUA Request for Examples Against Faculty, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Grievances, 1988-1994; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Institute for Social Research Personnel Data Survey, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Institutional Analysis of Affirmative Action Programs, undated (Box 1)
    - Merger, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Outside Regulatory Agencies Definitions of Terms Used by Outside Agencies, 1973-1981 (Box 1)
    - Personnel Support and Development Programs Monthly Activity Reports, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Plans for Evaluation of Harassment and Discrimination Policies, Barb Feldt files, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Racism Flyer, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - Analysis of Reports Alleging Discrimination or Discriminatory Harassment, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - SKILLS Inventory Affirmative Action Program for Employer and Under-Employed Minorities, 1979; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Sexual Discrimination Procedures, 1977-1981 (Box 2)
    - Sexual Harassment, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Summary of Pre-Grievance Contacts, 1986-1991 (Box 2)
    - Survey Data of the Affirmative Action Office, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Total Quality Diversity Program, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - Federal Agencies and Regulations
    The Federal Agencies and Regulations series (3.4 linear feet) (1964-1989) includes folders describing the university's interaction with the Department of Education, the Department of Labor, and the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission.
    The Department of Education administered Title IX ensuring that female athletes would have equal opportunities to participate in sports, with equal coaching, and training facilities, The Title IX records, covering the period 1972 to 1987, include the compliance reviews conducted by the university, correspondence between Virginia Nordby, university officials, and federal commissioners, and the federal regulations which the university was following. These records describe the history of athletics at the University of Michigan, budgets for the various programs, expenditures for the teams, financial aid available for the athletes, and information regarding their eligibility. Because of student-identifiable information, many of these folders are restricted.
    The Department of Labor, through the Office of Federal Contract Compliance Programs, directed that race and gender balances be established and maintained at the university, if federal funding through grants was to continue. These compliance reviews date from 1979 until 1988. They contain information about salaries, retention of current faculty and staff members, ways to increase the pool for under represented minorities and women, and selection criteria for newly hired personnel. Some of these records have been restricted.
    The Equal Employment Opportunity Commission oversaw the Age Discrimination Act and Equal Pay Acts. These records, covering the period from 1970-1989, document the university's role in insuring its employees fair treatment, including an undated paper written by Virginia Nordby interpreting the Equal Pay Act and Title VII legislation.
    - Summaries of Regulations, 1967-1980 (Box 2)
    - Commission for Civil Rights
      - General, 1972-1984 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Cases, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Department of Education
      - Age Discrimination Act
        - General Information, 1983 (Box 2)
        - Regulations, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
      - Commission on Civil Rights
        - Section 504
          - Cases and Other Information, 1977-1984 (Box 2)
          - Regulations, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
          - Self-Evaluation Final Draft, 1980 (Box 2)
        - Technical Assistance Services, 1984
        - Title VI
          - Cases and Other Information, 1974-1980 (Box 2)
          - Regulations, 1964-1979 (Box 2)
        - Title IX
          - Assurance, 1976 (Box 2)
          - Cases and Other Information, 1973-1983 (Box 2)
          - Civil Rights Restoration Act, 1987 (Box 2)
          - Compliance Review, 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 2)
          - Compliance Review, 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 22)
            [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2056 ]
          - Compliance Review, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
          - Correspondence, 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 3)
          - Compliance Review, 1982-1983; 3 folders (Box 22)
            [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2058 ]
          - Compliance Review, 1985-1986; 2 folders (Box 22)
            [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2061 ]
          - Regulations, 1972-1979 (Box 4)
    - Departments of Labor and Health, Education, and Welfare Consolidation, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Department of Labor
      - Office of Federal Contract Compliance Programs
        - Compliance, 1979 (Box 4)
        - Compliance On-Site Data Requests, 1980 (Box 4)
        - Compliance Review, 1985
          - Department of Labor Questions (Box 4)
          - Discharges and Salary Data (Box 22)
          - Minority Job Groups Information (Box 4)
          - Supplemental Data (Box 4)
          - Women's Job Groups Information (Box 4)
        - Compliance Review, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
        - Compliance Review, 1987 (Box 22)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2062 ]
        - Compliance Review, 1987 (Box 4)
        - Compliance Review, 1987 (Box 5)
        - Compliance Review Notes of Virginia Nordby, 1987 (Box 5)
        - Special Report, 1988 (Box 5)
        - Executive Order 11246
          - Cases and Other Information, 1972-1984 (Box 5)
          - Regulations, 1975-1981 (Box 5)
        - Section 402 (Veterans)
          - Cases and Other Information, 1974; 1976 (Box 5)
          - Regulations, 1976-1986 (Box 5)
      - Title IV, 1973-1979 (Box 5)
      - Women's Bureau, 1976-1978 (Box 5)
    - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission
      - Age Discrimination in Employment Act
        - Cases and Other Information, 1970-1980 (Box 5)
        - Regulations, 1974-1979 (Box 5)
      - Equal Pay Act Regulations, 1973-1980 (Box 5)
      - Title VII Regulations, 1972-1989 (Box 5)
  - Minorities
    - Council for Minority Affairs
      The Minorities series (1.4 linear feet) (1971-1995) includes records (1985-1988) describing incidents of racism on campus and the university's response. Included in this series is a folder of records documenting the Support Network for Affirmative Action Programs (SNAAP) begun at the Medical Center. Also included is a report from the 1984 executive officers retreat where the recruitment and retention of minority students was discussed.
      - Historical, 1977-1982 (Box 5)
    - Council on a Multicultural University (COMU)
      - Annual Reports, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 5)
      - Directions, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
      - Handouts, 1991 (Box 5)
      - Minutes, 1991-1995; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - President's Advisory Commission on Minority Affairs, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - Presidents Council
      - Minority Plan, 1982-1985 (Box 5)
    - Racial and Cultural Sensitivity Training
      - Articles about, 1985-1987; undated (Box 5)
      - General, 1985 (Box 5)
      - Printed Materials, 1971-1986 (Box 6)
    - Racism
      - Articles, 1983-1987 (Box 6)
      - Complaints, 1987-1988 (Box 22)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2018 ]
      - General, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
      - Hearing, 1987 (Box 6)
      - Letters of Commitment Against, 1987 (Box 6)
      - Training, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
      - WJJX Radio, 1986-1987 (Box 6)
      - SNAAP (Support Network for Affirmative Action Programs), 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - Students
      - Executive Officers Retreat regarding Minority Student Enrollment, 1984 (Box 6)
      - Feingold Report, 1981 (Box 6)
      - General, 1982-1988; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Surveys, 1980-1982; undated (Box 6)
  - Schools, Colleges and Other University Units
    The Schools and Colleges series (1.2 linear feet) (1972-1988) is arranged alphabetically. This series includes correspondence between the Affirmative Action Office and the schools and colleges discussing various policy issues such as faculty and staff hiring, retention, sabbatical leaves, retirements, and reduction-in-force. This series also contains more material on SNAPP which will be found under the heading "University Hospitals." Also included in this series are personnel data from the University of Michigan--Dearborn and University of Michigan--Flint.
    - Art School, 1985-1987 (Box 6)
    - Business Administration, 1973-1980 (Box 6)
    - Education, 1973-1984 (Box 6)
    - Engineering, 1975-1985 (Box 6)
    - Graduate School, 1976-1988 (Box 6)
    - Law School, 1975-1985 (Box 6)
    - LSA
      - Astronomy, 1979 (Box 6)
      - Chemistry, 1975-1980 (Box 6)
      - English Language and Literature, 1978-1981 (Box 6)
      - General, 1978-1988 (Box 7)
      - History, 1977-1980 (Box 7)
      - Museums, 1975 (Box 7)
      - Natural Science and Math, 1988 (Box 7)
      - Political Science, 1973-1978 (Box 7)
      - Psychology, 1976-1985 (Box 7)
      - Residential College, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Library Science, 1973-1986 (Box 7)
    - Medical School, 1975-1987 (Box 7)
    - Music School, 1975-1986 (Box 7)
    - Natural Resources
      - Black Students Association, 1975 (Box 7)
      - General, 1975-1985 (Box 7)
    - Nursing School
      - General, 1975-1988 (Box 7)
      - Salary Equity Study, 1985 (Box 7)
    - Pharmacy, 1975-1985 (Box 7)
    - Physical Education, 1984 (Box 7)
    - Public Health
      - Affirmative Action Advisory Committee, 1972-1980 (Box 7)
      - General, 1975-1985 (Box 7)
    - Social Work, 1975-1986 (Box 7)
    - Units within the University
      - Athletics, 1976-1986 (Box 7)
      - Center for Afro-American and African Affairs, 1977-1985 (Box 7)
      - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Division of Research Development and Administration, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
      - Institutes
        - Gerontology, 1976-1984 (Box 7)
        - Institute for Social Research, 1973-1987 (Box 7)
        - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities, 1973-1975 (Box 7)
        - Institute of Science and Technology, 1984-1986 (Box 7)
        - Libraries, 1972-1988 (Box 7)
        - Office of Student Services, 1975-1977 (Box 7)
      - University Hospitals
        - General, 1972-1987; 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Medical Records and Information Department, 1972; undated (Box 7)
        - SNAAP (Support Network for Affirmative Action Programs), 1979-1982 (Box 7)
      - University of Michigan--Dearborn
        - Affirmative Action Committee, 1975-1981 (Box 7)
        - Committee for Women, 1976-1980 (Box 7)
        - Enrollment/Employee Data for Females and Minorities, 1974-1978 (Box 7)
        - General, 1975-1986; 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Personnel Data, 1978 (Box 7)
      - University of Michigan--Flint, 1974-1982 (Box 7)
  - State of Michigan
    - Cushingberry Inquiry, 1978-1980
      - Correspondence (Box 8)
      - Resource Documents (Box 8)
    - Department of Education
      - General, 1978-1985 (Box 8)
    - Equal Employment and Business Opportunity Council
      - General, 1985 (Box 8)
    - Governor's Task Force on Minority Enrollment in Higher Education
      - General, 1980 (Box 8)
    - Holmes Inquiry
      - General, 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Resource Documents, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
    - Hood Inquiry on Racism
      - General, 1985 (Box 8)
      - Resource Documents, 1985 (Box 8)
      - General, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Hunter Inquiry
      - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 8)
    - Michigan State Civil Rights Commission
      - Certificate of Awardability, 1978-1984 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 8)
      - Hearing, 1988 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous, 1988; 1991 (Box 8)
    - Special Committee on Affirmative Action
      - General, 1979; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - State Superintendent's Special Committee on Minorities, Women, and Handicappers
      - General, 1985 (Box 8)
  - Women
    The Affirmative Action Office worked closely with women's groups on campus. The Women series (3 linear feet) (1970-2001) documents that relationship with records of the Academic Women's Caucus, the Center for the Continuing Education of Women (later known as the Center for the Education of Women), the Commission for Women (CFW), and the Women's Information Group (WING). These records are arranged alphabetically. The Academic Women's Caucus (1974-2001) includes records documenting the process of awarding the Sarah Goddard Power Award including nominations from 1989 to 2001. There are also minutes for the period from 1982 to 1987, as well as copies of the reports Report on the Status of Women and Status of Female Faculty, both released in 1982. The CEW includes correspondence, minutes of meetings, and publications dating from 1979-1988. The Commission for Women (1980-1998) includes career guides, correspondence, minutes and agendas, and publications. The Women's Information Group (1983-1989) includes correspondence, minutes and agendas, and publications. There are also records documenting important women's issues in this series including child care, discrimination, the Equal Rights Amendment, rape prevention, and the status of women in graduate education.
    - Academic Women's Caucus
      - Awards, 1984-1988 (Box 9)
      - Committees
        - General and Awards Committees
          - 1988-1992, 3 folders (Box 9)
          - 1996 (Box 9)
        - Sarah Goddard Power Award Nominations, 1989-2001; 3 folders (Box 9)
        - Steering Committee, 1987-1988 (Box 9)
      - General, 1974-1988 (Box 9)
      - Minutes, 1982-1987 (Box 9)
      - Orientation, 1982-1983 (Box 9)
      - Primary Research Faculty, 1983 (Box 9)
      - Report on the Status of Women, 1982 (Box 9)
      - Status of Female Faculty, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Advancement and Promotion, 1979 (Box 10)
    - CEW (Continuing Education for Women/Center for the Education of Women)
      - Daphne Bennett Talk, 1986 (Box 10)